<?xml version="1.0"?>
<records>
<record>
<language>eng</language>
<publisher>German Multidisciplinary Publishing Center</publisher>
<journalTitle>German Journal of Veterinary Research</journalTitle>
<issn/>
<publicationDate>2020-03-01</publicationDate>
<volume>2</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<startPage>1</startPage>
<endPage>5</endPage>
<doi>1025</doi>
<publisherRecordId>24156</publisherRecordId>
<documentType/>
<title language="eng">Combined H5ND inactivated vaccine protects chickens against challenge by different clades of highly pathogenic avian influenza viruses subtype H5 and virulent Newcastle disease virus</title>
<authors>
<author>
<name>Ahmed Ali</name>
<email>-</email>
<affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
</author>
<author>
<name>Ahmed So</name>
<email>-</email>
<affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
</author>
</authors>
<affiliationsList>
<affiliationName affiliationId="1">2 Anwar Hassan street</affiliationName>
</affiliationsList>
<abstract language="eng">Aim: The aim of the current study was to evaluate a trivalent inactivated oil-emulsion vaccine against different clades highly pathogenic avian influenza (AI) viruses including AI-H5N8 and the virulent genotype VII NDV virus (vNDV). Materials and methods: the vaccine studied herein is composed of AI viruses rg A/Chicken/Egypt/ME1010/2016 (clade 2.2.1.1), H5N1 rgA/Chicken/Egypt/RG-173CAL/2017 (clade 2.2.1.2) and Newcastle disease virus NDV (LaSota NDV/CK/Egypt/11478AF/11); all used at a concentration of 108 EID50/bird and mixed with Montanide-ISA70 oil adjuvant. Two weeks old Specific Pathogen Free (SPF) chickens were immunized subcutaneously with 0.5 ml of the vaccine and hemagglutination inhibition (HI) antibody titers were monitored weekly. Intranasal challenge was conducted 4 weeks post vaccination (PV) using 106EID50/0.1ml of the different virulent AI-H5N1 viruses representing clades 2.2.1, 2.2.1.1, 2.2.1.2, 2.3.4.4b-H5N8 and the vNDV. Results: the vaccine induced HI antibody titers of &gt;6log2 against H5N1 and NDV viruses 2 weeks post vaccination. There was a clinical protection of 100% against all H5N1 viruses and vNDV, whereas 93.3% protection was found against HPAI H5 clade-2.2.1 and HPAI H5 clade-2.3.4.4b viruses. Challenged birds showed a significant decrease in the titer of virus shedding [Ger. J. Vet. Res. 2020; 2(1.000): 1-5]</abstract>
<fullTextUrl format="pdf">222-1604226191.pdf</fullTextUrl>
<keywords language="eng">
<keyword>Avian influenza</keyword>
<keyword>H5N1</keyword>
<keyword>H5N8</keyword>
<keyword>Newcastle diseases virus</keyword>
<keyword>H5ND</keyword>
<keyword>Trivalent vaccine</keyword>
<keyword>Egypt</keyword>
</keywords>
</record>
</records>